Guide to the W.H. Cowley Papers SC0196
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
W.H. Cowley papers
1913-1978
bulk
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Cowley, W. H. (William Harold)
SC0196
200 Linear Feet
Collection includes extensive correspondence with leaders in the pioneer field of higher education, administrative papers from Cowley's various positions in college administrations, materials on the history, administration and taxonomy of higher education, outlines from lectures given at Stanford, and a series of research notebooks kept by Cowley on the subject of higher education. The collection also includes published and unpublished articles, papers, speeches, and reports.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Mrs. W.H. Cowley and Ellen Cowley, 1978.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
WW.H. (Hal) Cowley was born in Petersburg, Virginia on May 28, 1899. Shortly thereafter his family moved to New. York City where he lived until the age of twenty-one. He graduated from Dartmouth College in 1924, and received his Ph. D. in 1930 from the University of Chicago. Although he took his advanced degree in Psychology, an interest in higher education (which had been growing since his undergraduate days at Dartmouth) led to a succession of jobs in college administration: as Assistant to the President and Head of Placement Services, briefly, at the University of Chicago, as a professor of Psychology with the Educational Research Bureau at Ohio State University from 1931 through 1937, and as President of Hamilton College from 1938 to 1944.
Cowley found his work in higher education administration challenging, but saw an increasing need for quality researchers in the field. Thus, in 1945 he came to Stanford University as the the first professor of higher education in the United States, to devote the remainder of his career to teaching and research. He became David Jacks Professor of Higher Education at Stanford in 1954 and emeritus in 1968.
Description of the Collection
Collection includes extensive correspondence with leaders in the pioneer field of higher education, administrative papers from Cowley's various positions in college administrations, materials on the history, administration and taxonomy of higher education, outlines from lectures given at Stanford, and a series of research notebooks kept by Cowley on the subject of higher education. The collection also includes published and unpublished articles, papers, speeches, and reports.
The Cowley Papers span the years 1922 through 1978, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the years 1940 to 1970. The papers have been divided into three series, with subdivisions within the particular series.
Series I consists of the personal papers and writings of Professor Cowley. These include'correspondence, both personal and professional, from 1922-1978, drafts of papers and articles', published papers and articles, speech outlines, book manuscripts in various stages of completion, and newsclippings. The highlight of this series is Professor Cow1ey 1s correspondence with other leaders in the then-pioneer field of higher education. Also notable are the many drafts from three as yet unpublished books. Written about the history, government, and taxonomy, respectively, of higher education, these books are the product of years of exhaustive research efforts on Professor Cow1ey·s part to disp~ the myths and establish the facts surrounding American higher education. In them are embodied many (but by no means all) of the ideas which engaged Mr. Cowley·s interest throughout his career. Professor Cowley had organized these materials chronologically, and this order has been maintained. For this reason, no attempt has been made to separate or organize this series by type of material (e.g. making the correspondence a separate series from his articles or papers).
Series II consists of Cowley's research 'tools': his system of PN, F and PT files, and the workbooks which organized and analyzed these files. The PN, or 'professional notes', files fill six filing cabinets and are notes taken from books. or articles read by Professor Cowley. The F files are similar in content to PN files, but are larger, measuring SJa" X 11" rather than 8" X 5" as do the PN's. The workbooks are binders on different topics that interested Professor Cowley. Each page in a binder was a subdivision of the ge~eral workbook topic. Each entry on a page was a short excerpt from a source whose bibliographic reference was always included. From these research aids, Professor Cowley produced the more than 250 articles and papers in Series I.
Series III consists of detailed lecture outlines, many of them bound and indexed, for courses in higher education taught by Professor Cowley at Stanford from the years 1945 to 1968.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged in eight series: I-A Biographical material (1899-1978); I-B Correspondence, writings and speeches (1922-1978); I-C Miscellaneous correspondence (1922-1978); I-D Papers (1928-1971); I-E Lecture series (1945-1968); II-A Professional notes (1900-1978); II-B 'PT' files (pamphlets) (1813-1975); II-C Workbooks (1938-1978).
General note
Cowley's collection of pamphlets was also reboxed, maintaining the numerical sequence of the numbers he assigned them. No box listing was compiled for the pamphlets.
Chronology
Chronology
1899 born, Petersburg, Virginia
1978 died, Palo Alto, California
1964-1978 David Jacks Professor of Higher Education, emeritus, Stanford University
1954-1964 David Jacks Professor of Higher Education, Stanford University
1951-1952 Fullbright scholarship to study academic government of British universities
1945-1954 Professor of Higher Education, Stanford University
1942 Chairman, Committee of War Manpower Commission and U.S. Office of Education to develope a plan for the wartime use of colleges and universities
1939-1943 member, Problems and Plans Committee, American Council on Education
1943 Received LL.D from St. Lawrence University
1939 received L.H.D. from Hobart College
1938 received L.L.D. from Hamilton College
1938-1944 President of Hamilton College
1935-1938 Professor of Pyschology, Ohio State University
1934-1935 Associate Professor of Pyschology, Ohio state University
1934 married Jean McCampbell
1929-1934 Research Associate and Assistant Professor of Pyschology, Bureau of Educational Research, Ohio State University
1930 earned Ph.D. in pyschology from the University of Chicago
1927-1929 employed on administrative staff, University of Chicago; Board of Vocational Guidance and Placement
1924-1925 employed by Bell Telephone Labs., New York
1924 graduation from Dartmouth College, A.B. in English editor, The Dartmouth, the Dartmouth College newspaper
College teachers.; Educators.; Education, Higher.; Cowley, W. H. (William Harold); University of Chicago.; Cowley, W. H. (William Harold); Hamilton College (Clinton, N.Y.); Stanford University; Ohio State University.
- Personal papers and writings, Series 1
  - Biographical material, 1899-1978; Series 1A
    Scope and Contents note
    Thlis series contains biographical information about Professor W.H. Cowley. It consists of articles about Cowley, some autobiographical writings and an oral history transcript. The oral history of Cowley was done by the Columbia Oral History Project in 1961.
    - Binder of miscellaneous information selected by WHC. Includes articles, excerpts from correspondence, documents relating to his career, summaries of important events in his life written by WHC, honorary degree citations., 1922-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Volume 1 of WHC's Reminiscences, transcript of an oral history done at the request of Columbia University Oral History Project., 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Volume 2 of Reminiscences. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Projects binder: describes and summarizes a variety of WHC's concerns during his career. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Biographical articles, most written after WHC's death., after 1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Genealogical information on the Cowley family. Much of it on unorganized, handwritten notes. Includes unidentified photos, probably of WHC as a young child. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, writings and speeches, 1922-1978; Series 1B
    Cowley organized his personal and professional correspondence, his manuscripts, articles and speeches into one chronological series. Because his folder numbers are referenced throughout his large and intricate research series, any attempt to reorganize the material, separating the correspondence and writings into distinct series, would not only obscure Cowley's own very definite ideas about the organization of his papers but would also cripple his elaborate information retrieval system. Instead, the original order was maintained. Correspondence, articles and speeches with related correspondence, and manuscripts are arranged in folders withl~cession numbers. The first two numbers designate the year of the accession; the remainder is an item number within a given year. For example the folder number, 22-15, would indicate that the material was the 15th item accessioned in 1922.
    - 41 editorials written by WHC as editor of the Dartmouth College student newspaper., 1922 (Box 1, Folder 22-1)
    - 14 of WHC's course papers from Dartmouth. Also includes an article, "Graceful Juniorhead," written for The Twenty-Four Hour Notice., 1923 (Box 1, Folder 23-1)
    - Notes and correspondence about The Dartmouth banquet, including comments on speeches given there by WHC and by the President of Dartmouth, Hopkins, Ernest Martin., 1923 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 23-1A)
    - Correspondence with Hopkins, E.M. President of Dartmouth College., 1923-1924 (Box not specified, Folder 23-2)
    - WHC letter to professor Richardson, Leon B. giving his reactions to the Emery Report of the Dartmouth Faculty Committee on Educational Policy. Also contains letters from Richardson, L.B. to WHC., 1923 Dec (Box 1, Folder 23-3)
    - Maclean, Norman caricature of WHC in a Dartmouth student publication, The Jack-O-Lantern. See also 24-6., 1923 Dec 28 (Box 1, Folder 23-4)
    - "College Teaching," memo to self., 1923 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 23-5)
    - WHC's editorials for The Dartmouth., 1923 (Box 1, Folder 23-6)
    - "The Fundamental Facts," WHC editorial for The Dartmouth greeting Bryan, William Jennings upon his visit to Dartmouth College. Also contains newsclippings about Bryan's visit., 1923 Dec (Box 1, Folder 23-7)
    - Dartmouth Senior Committee Report: Part I, 45 pages, written by WHC and 11 other seniors. See also 24-3, 24-8, 24-13. (Box 1, Folder 24-1)
    - Papers related to the initiation and sequel of WHC 24-1, including copies of the Emery Committee Report, La Critique, and E.M.Hopkins and Fran Ruml letters., 1923-1924 (Box 1, Folder 24-1A)
    - WHC editorials for The Dartmouth., 1924 (Box 1, Folder 24-2)
    - "The Dartmouth College Senior Committee Report: Part II." 148 typed pages. Never published or reproduced. See also 24-13., 1924-1925 (Box 1, Folder 24-3)
    - Miscellaneous comments about the Dartmouth Senior Committee Report and the quality of WHC's writing., 1925 (Box 1, Folder 24-4)
    - Miscellaneous papers relating to The Dartmouth: correspondence about WHC's editorials, list of editorials written by WHC, and copies of some of them., 1923, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 24-5)
    - Cartoons of WHC drawn by Geisel, Ted (who later wrote the Dr. Seuss books). Cartoon was Norman Maclean's suggestion. See also 23-4., 1924 (Box 1, Folder 24-6)
    - Correspondence with Dubois, Charles S., President of the Western Electric Company, and with his son, Bill (a classmate of WHC's at Dartmouth) and his daughter, Sue., 1925 Mar-Oct (Box 1, Folder 24-7)
    - Correspondence. With Shea, Frank a Dartmouth classmate who became the dean of the University of Buffalo Law School and later, Assistant Attorney General under Roosevelt, Franklin., 1924 Jul-Dec (Box 1, Folder 24-8)
    - Correspondence with Judge Anderson, George W. and his son, Bob, a Dartmouth classmate. Judge Anderson was judge of the U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals, Boston., 1924 Sep-1925 Dec (Box 1, Folder 24-9)
    - Correspondence and WHC diary entries about WHC's University of Wesleyan speech. Also includes newsclippings., 1924-1925 (Box 1, Folder 24-10)
    - Correspondence with Gavit, John Palmer and Mrs. Gavit., 1925 (Box 1, Folder 24-11)
    - Papers relating to the finances of Dartmouth: Correspondence and balance sheets., 1924 May-Oct (Box 1, Folder 24-12)
    - Correspondence about the suppression of Part II of the Dartmouth Senior Committee Report. See also 24-1 and 24-3., 1924 Sep-1925 Oct (Box 1, Folder 24-13)
    - Miscellaneous papers including WHC voted "Done the Most for Dartmouth" and "Most Likely to Succeed." Also includes WHC's passport, results of his physical examination, Dartmouth Commencement program, Alpha Delta Phi annual chapter letter., 1924 (Box 1, Folder 24-14)
    - Dartmouth yearbooks, The Aegis and The Greenbook, and related pictures., 1923-1926 (Box 1, Folder 24-15)
    - Analysis of the course in English Composition taught by WHC as part of his job at Bell Labs. 26 typed pages., 1925 (Box 1, Folder 25-1)
    - Papers and correspondence about Dartmouth's literary magazine, The Tower which was started partly because of WHC's efforts, the year after his graduation. Correspondents include Dick Eberhart, Jack Altizer and others. This folder also contains an article, "The New Curriculum" written by WHC and included in the issue of The Tower, 5 printed pages., 1925 Nov 6 (Box 1, Folder 25-2)
    - Correspondence with Hopkins, E.M.., 1925 (Box 2, Folder 25-3)
    - Pamphlet, "Selecting and Placing College Graduates in Business," written by Mills, John that WHC quoted, 27 printed pages., 1925 (Box 2, Folder 25-4)
    - WHC memo, "The Proposed Medical Department of the Bell Telephone Labs." Blueprints are included in the text, 23 pages., 1925 Jun 27 (Box 2, Folder 25-6)
    - WHC article "Twenty Courtship Axioms." Written under pseudonym, Degraw, Douglas. Sent to magazines, but never published, 13 typed pages., circa 1924 (Box 2, Folder 25-7)
    - Correspondence regarding The Dartmouth and WHC's post-graduation relationship to it., 1925 Jan-1971 Feb (Box 2, Folder 25-8)
    - Correspondence about WHC's career problems., 1925 Jan-1926 Oct (Box 2, Folder 25-9)
    - Correspondence about invitation to lead discussions of the National Student Forum at their summer conferences., 1925 Apr-Jul (Box 2, Folder 25-10)
    - WHC article, "Explaining the Rah Rah Boy," published in the New Republic. Also includes long diary entry about it., 1926 Apr 14 (Box 2, Folder 26-1)
    - Transcript of WHC talk, "The New Psychology," given for the American Legion, Chicago., 1926 Apr 12 (Box 2, Folder 26-2)
    - WHC course paper "A Study of Retroactive Inhibition," University of Chicago., 1926 Aug 26 (Box 2, Folder 26-3)
    - WHC's personal analysis and diary entries., 1924-1926 (Box 2, Folder 26-4)
    - WHC course paper, "Psychology and Ethics," University of Chicago., 1926 Aug 26 (Box 2, Folder 26-5)
    - Miscellaneous folders:, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 26-6)
    - WHC notes on college traditions., 1926 (Box 2, Folder 26-6A)
    - Correspondence about employment at the YMCA College in Chicago., 1926 Jun-Aug (Box 2, Folder 26-6B)
    - Correspondence with Judge Anderson, George B. about Mayo, Elton and Judge Anderson's son Bob., 1926 Apr-Nov (Box 2, Folder 26-6C)
    - List of books read by WHC., 1926 (Box 2, Folder 26-6D)
    - Miscellaneous. diary notes, including some about Commager, H.S.., 1926 (Box 2, Folder 26-6E)
    - Correspondence about Dartmouth Senior Committee Report., 1924 (Box 2, Folder 26-7)
    - Correspondence with Duffy, Ed and Eberhart, Dick. Folder also contains editorials from The Dartmouth written by Duffy, Ed and WHC's responses to them., 1926 (Box 2, Folder 26-7A)
    - Duffy, Ed article in Intercollegiate World, "A Critical Survey of The Dartmouth Report.", 1926 Mar (Box 2, Folder 26-7B)
    - Clippings from The Dartmouth, including two letters to the editor from Marks, Percy and the editor's responses concerning the proper balance between extracurricular activities and intellectual pursuits., 1926 Nov-Dec (Box 2, Folder 26-7C)
    - WHC review of Percy Marks' " Which Way Parnassus?" published in the New Republic, pages 177-178. folder also contains correspondence with Lovett, R.M., 1927 (Box 2, Folder 27-1)
    - Correspondence with Hopkins, E.M. about the second half of the Dartmouth Senior Committee Report., 1927 (Box 2, Folder 27-2)
    - Notes for a WHC course paper, "Psychology as Art and Science"., 1926-1927 (Box 2, Folder 27-3)
    - Course Paper: "The Social Implications of L.L. Thurstone's 'The Nature of Intelligence.' " Also includes L.L. Thurstone's and Professor George Mead's reactions to it., 1927 (Box 2, Folder 27-4)
    - Copy of WHC course paper, "The Emotions," University of Chicago., 1927 May 23 (Box 2, Folder 27-5)
    - WHC course paper, "The Will," University of Chicago., 1927 (Box 2, Folder 27-6)
    - Dartmouth editorial quoting WHC-Bryan editorial. See also 23-7., circa 1927 (Box 2, Folder 27-7)
    - WHC report on his leadership study to Professor Merriam, C.F. 11 pages., 1927 Feb 21 (Box 2, Folder 27-8)
    - University of Chicago Employment: (Box 2, Folder 27-9)
    - WHC review of University of Chicago Employment. MISSING (Box 2, Folder 27-9A)
    - Correspondence With University of Chicago President Mason, Max., 1927 Apr-Aug (Box 2, Folder 27-9B)
    - Notes on Max Mason's and WHC's ideas., undated (Box 2, Folder 27-9C)
    - WHC nomination as Director of the University of Chicago Board of Vocational Guidance and Placement., 1927 Jul 13 (Box 2, Folder 27-9D)
    - Letters home to Mrs. Gavit about Mason, Max proposal., 1927 Aug 5-18 (Box 2, Folder 27-9E)
    - WHC memo as executive Secretary of the Board of Vocational Guidance and Placement., 1927 Oct 15 (Box 2, Folder 27-9F)
    - WHC paper, "Three Distinctions in the Study of Leaders." Read to the New York city Bureau of Personnel Administration, published in book cited in 31-18. See also 28-1., 1927, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 27-10)
    - WHC article, "Three Distinctions in the Study of Leaders," published in the Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology, 14 pages. See also 27-10., 1928 Jul-Sep (Box 2, Folder 28-1)
    - The Profession of Librarianship with Timmerman, H.B., published in The American Council on Education Vocational Monograph Series., 1928 Nov (Box 2, Folder 28-2)
    - WHC course paper, "Obsessions," University of Chicago., 1928 Mar 31 (Box 2, Folder 28-3)
    - WHC course paper, "Reasoning" for Systematic Psychology course, University of Chicago., 1928 Winter (Box 2, Folder 28-4)
    - List of University of Chicago administrators with WHC in sixth place. Also contains related correspondence., 1928 Jun-Nov (Box 2, Folder 28-5)
    - WHC course paper, "Hysteria," 7 pages, University of Chicago., 1928 Mar 12 (Box 2, Folder 28-6)
    - WHC course paper, "The Will," 19 pages, University of Chicago., undated (Box 2, Folder 28-7)
    - Course paper, "Perception," 11 pages., 1928 Mar 12 (Box 3, Folder 28-8)
    - Correspondence with Dartmouth administrators, Dean Craven Laycock, Dean W.R. Gray, and President Ernest Martin Hopkins about WHC's Chicago study and job., 1928 Feb 3 (Box 3, Folder 28-9)
    - Maclean, Norm correspondence about WHC's recommendation of him for University of Chicago English Department position., 1928 Sep-1932 May (Box 3, Folder 28-10)
    - WHC application for Ohio State University (OSU) position as junior dean and related correspondence Includes biographical review of WHC., 1928 Apr-Jun (Box 3, Folder 28-11)
    - Correspondence with Charters, W.W. about WHC's librarianship article and his writing ability. See also 28-2., 1928 Jun (Box 3, Folder 28-12)
    - AT&T study, "Does Business Want Scholars?" written by Bridgeman, Don for President Gifford and published in Harper's Magazine. Includes WHC letter to Rees, R.I. criticizing it., 1928 (Box 3, Folder 28-13)
    - Correspondence with Kennan, Jack about efforts to ge help placing black students., 1928 Nov 15-22 (Box 3, Folder 28-14)
    - Miscellaneous folders:, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 28-15)
    - Correspondence about WHC's Ph.D. Dissertation on leadership., 1928 (Box 3, Folder 28-15A)
    - Correspondence with President Holt, Hamilton of Rollins College about the Dartmouth Senior Committee Report., 1928 Apr 19 (Box 3, Folder 28-15B)
    - Correspondence about University of Pittsburg Dean of Men position., 1928 Jul (Box 3, Folder 28-15C)
    - Correspondence about Bravig Imb's "The Professor's Wife"., 1928 Dec (Box 3, Folder 28-15D)
    - Correspondence with Professor Hagbolt and WHC method of studying German., 1928 Jul (Box 3, Folder 28-15E)
    - Correspondence about WHC's cousin, Harry Monk's invention of submarine rescue apparatus., 1928 Sep-1929 Jan (Box 3, Folder 28-15F)
    - List of books read., 1928 (Box 3, Folder 28-15G)
    - WHC article, "The University Establishes a New Administrative Office," Published in The University of Chicago Magazine., 1929 Mar (Box 3, Folder 29-1)
    - WHC article, "A Technique for Analyzing the Supply and Demand for Educational Workers." Co-authored by Grant, Albert. Published in School and Society, 3 pages., 1929 May 19 (Box 3, Folder 29-2)
    - The Spirit of the College, WHC talk at the University of Chicago Chapel, 9 typed pages., 1929 May 31 (Box 3, Folder 29-3)
    - WHC course paper, "Current Trends in Theoretical Psychology and Psychology of Personality," University of Chicago, 11 typed pages., 1929 Aug 29 (Box 3, Folder 29-4)
    - WHC report "The Board of Vocational Guidance and Placement," report to the president of the University of Chicago, 9 typed pages., 1929 (Box 3, Folder 29-5)
    - WHC's review of "The Choice of an Occupation," by Crawford, A.B., published in The Personnel Journal, Vol. 8., 1929 (Box 3, Folder 29-6)
    - Report of WHC speech on leadership, Chicago. Newsclippings also included., 1929 Jun (Box 3, Folder 29-7)
    - Young, Arthur H. speech of citing WHC's "The Study of Leadership." See also 28-1., 1929 May 6 (Box 3, Folder 29-8)
    - Papers related to WHC's University of Chicago position with the Board of Vocational Guidance and Placement, and his resignation from., 1929 (Box 3, Folder 29-9)
    - Papers related to WHC's negotiations with and appointment to the Ohio State University faculty. Includes correspondence with the University of Chicago about resignation from job there., 1929 Jun-Sep (Box 3, Folder 29-10)
    - Miscellaneous folders:, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 29-11)
    - WHC letter to Hawkes, Louise Padelford telling her of his recommendation of her for Scripps College faculty, English department., 1929 Jan 14 (Box 3, Folder 29-11A)
    - WHC letter to Jordan, Frances Ruml telling her of his recommendation of her to Scripps College Economics Faculty., 1929 Jan-Nov (Box 3, Folder 29-11B)
    - Correspondence with Dickson, Campbell., 1929 Jan-Oct (Box 3, Folder 29-11C)
    - Correspondence about WHC review of book for University of Chicago Press., 1929 Apr (Box 3, Folder 29-11D)
    - WHC letter to Gavit, John Palmer about the new University of Chicago President Hutchins, R.M.., 1929 May 11 (Box 3, Folder 29-11E)
    - Correspondence with Charters, W.W.., 1927-1929 (Box 3, Folder 29-11F)
    - WHC letter to Little, Alene at Constantinople Women's College. Discusses new Univeristy of Chicago president Hutchins, Robert Maynard., 1929 May 8 (Box 3, Folder 29-11G)
    - WHC paper, "A Survey of the Personnel Activities of the Ohio State University," 42 pages., 1930 May 31 (Box 3, Folder 30-1)
    - "The History of American College Calendar," WHC 18 pages. See also 32-2., undated (Box 3, Folder 30-2)